Thorp & Dickson mss., ca. 1831 LMC 2703
Lilly Library
Thorp & Dickson mss.
1831
Lilly Library
Thorp & Dickson (Firm)
LMC 2703
1 Box 1 standard
The Thorp & Dickson mss., 1831, consists of materials relating to the organizing of anti-reform petitions in the County of Northumberland in response to the Representation of the People Act 1832.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Historical Note
The Great Reform Act aimed to redistribute electoral representation in England and Wales from low-population rural boroughs controlled by the nobility and gentry to new and rapidly expanding industrial centers. The reform expanded eligibility to vote to small landowners, tenant farmers, shopkeepers, and householders who paid a yearly rental of £10 or more, and to some lodgers. The reform also explicitly disenfranchised women for the first time by defining voters as male persons.
Thorp & Dickson were solicitors of Alnwick, Northumberland, who coordinated the opposition in the County to the Reform Bill on behalf of the Duke of Northumberland.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of materials relating to organizing anti-reform petitions in the County of Northumberland. The collection includes correspondence, billing statements and notes pertaining to the gathering of petitioners' signatures. The "List of Names" contains in excess of 8,200 names (2,296 "to the King"; 2,406 "to House of Lords"; and approximately 2,500 "to the Commons"), with the occupation of the petitioner occasionally stated, as well as a town-by-town index. Documents in the collection cover practically the entire process of drawing up a petition, from letters in which individuals agree to the inclusion of their names, to the stationer's receipt for the vellum on which the petition is transcribed. Additionally, there are numerous itemized bills of charges and letters from other solicitors engaged by Thorp & Dickson to collect petitioners' signatures. Also included are several letters from Thorp & Dickson acknowledging payment of bills by Sir David William Smith (the Duke's land agent). Printed items in the collection include copies of Bills 14 and 15, March 1831, "To amend the Representation of the People", the first in England and Wales, and the second in Scotland, as well as a printed document "Extracted from the Commission of the Peace for the County of Northumberland", 6 November 1831.
For digitized content, see Digital Collections.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 2010
Great Britain --Politics and Government --1800-1837.; Great Britain. Representation of the People Act (1832).; voting; Great Britain; Northumberland, Hugh Percy, Duke of, 1785-1847.; Smith, David William, Sir, 1764-1837.
- Collection (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 3-5 April 1831 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 6-9 April 1831 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 10-11 April 1831 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 12-13 April 1831 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 14-15 April 1831 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 16-26 April 1831 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1-21 May 1831 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 22-30 May 1831,undated (Box 1)
  - Lists of petitioners, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Printed material, "Bill to amend the representation of the people in England and Wales", 14 March 1831 (Box 1)
  - Printed material, "Bill to amend the representation of the people in Scotland", 15 March 1831 (Box 1)
  - Printed material, "Mr. Hunt's Speech, delivered in the House of Commons", 12 April 1831; (2 copies) (Box 1)
  - Printed material, "Extracted from the Commission of the Peace for the County of Northumberland", 6 November 1831 (Box 1)
  - Notes and drafts of petitions (Box 1)
  - Billing statements (Box 1)